你好黑客
hello hackers
欢迎收看PWN学院的视频
welcome to another video in pwn college
今天我们将结束竞争条件模块
today we're wrapping up the race conditions module
最后讲一下信号量和重入
with the signals and reentrancy video
回想一下
think back to
在整个课程中对信号量的使用方式
throughout this course where you've interacted with signals in one way or another
尤其是在介绍进程生命周期的基础课中
but especially through to the fundamentals lecture about the process lifecycle
讨论了信号量的原理
where I discussed how signals work
如何发送信号给进程等等
how they might be sent to a process etc
如果你还记得，那节课讲的信号
if you recall back in that lecture I talked about how a signal is
从某种意义上说，基本上就是一种信息
basically a message in some sense
一种在进程间传递的信息
a message with an oomph from one process to another
进程可以通过kill系统调用向另一个进程发送信号
a process can send a signal to another process by using the kill system call
Kill系统调用有2个参数
kill system call takes 2 argument
接收方进程id
the recipient process id
以及要发送的信号量
and the signal to send
发送的信号量就是一个数值常数
the signal to send is basically a numerical constant
它用于表示不同的信号
that encodes a bunch of different types of signals
不同类型的信号有不同的
and different types of signals have different
效果和语义
effects and different semantic intense basically
例如
for example
我可以发....
I can send a ....
如果在shell上使用kill命令
if you use the kill command on your shell. the kill utility
且没有指定要发送的信号
and you don't specify a signal to kill
它将发送SIGTERM信号给接收方进程
it'll send what is called a SIGTERM signal  to the recipient process
该信号的默认处理动作是终止进程
the default action of this signal is to kill the process
另一方面，如果你发送SIGSTOP
on the other hand if you send a SIGSTOP
它是少数无法更改处理动作的信号
the only action it's impossible to change
它将停止接收方进程
this action will be to stop that process
之后你可以用 SIGCONT 继续接收方进程
and then you can continue it by sending a SIGCONT
有很多不同的信号
there's a bunch of different signals
我讲一下信号 SIGALRM
let me show you real quick one signal SIGALRM
如果我们
if we
alarm_me.c
有一个主程序
and we have a main program
调用 alarm 设置超时时间，单位为秒
you can call alarm to set a time out in seconds
超时后程序会收到 SIGALRM
after which an alarm signal will trigger and be sent to your program
所以如果调用 alarm 然后开始死循环
so if we make an alarm and then we loop forever
运行一下
all right let's run it
一秒钟后
after one second
输出了Alarm clock
we get the printing alarm clock
并且程序终止了
the printout alarm clock and the program terminates
这是 SIGALRM 的默认处理动作
that is the default action of the SIGALRM clock
有很多不同的信号
and there's a bunch of different signals
这个还不是最全的
this isn't the exhausted list
可以运行 kill -l  查看完整列表
the exhaustive list you can run kill -l to print out all of the signals
在你整个计算机科学生涯中能遇到的信号都在里面
that you might have to deal with throughout your computer science career
可以在 google 等处查看其完整文档记录
they're well documented on Google and probably many other places
让我们继续
let's roll forward
这是信号列表
so these are signals
这是发送信号的方法
this is how to send signals
我一直在说信号的默认处理动作
now I keep saying the default action of a signal
比如 SIGALRM 的默认动作是输出 Alarm clock
such as signal alarm for example is to print alarm clock
实际上，你可以更改他们
well it turns out you can change these actions
注册一个函数
you can register a function
它会在接收到信号后运行
that will be run when you receive a signal
你可以为每个信号注册一个函数
you can register a function for every signal
除了 SIGKILL 和 SIGSTOP
except for SIGKILL and SIGSTOP
这两个信号是无法捕捉到的（无法更改）
those two signals are impossible to capture
注册一个信号处理程序
you register a signal handler
当接收到信号后
what happens when you trigger it
进程执行会立即暂停
is that your process execution will immediately pause
然后信号处理程序将被调用
and your signal handler will be invoked
看一下实际效果
let's take a look at what this might look like
我给我们写了一个 alarm.c 程序
I wrote us an alarm.c
注册了一个 SIGALRM 的处理程序
that registers a signal handler for my alarm
处理程序会
and it says
输出全大写的ALARM，而不是Alarm clock
it'll print alarm in all caps instead Alarm clock
然后退出，错误码为42
and exit with the error code 42
编译
let's compile that
运行
run it
1、2
1 2 boom
好了
and there we go
退出代码是42
exit code 42
所以利用注册处理程序，几乎可以捕获任意信号
so we can successfully capture almost any signal by registering a handler
有两种方法可以注册处理程序
there are two ways to do it
最简单的方法是使用 signal 函数
the easy way is to use the signal function
signal函数只要 signum 和 handler函数 两个参数
signal is a function that just takes a signal number and a function
它会执行 handler函数，并传给它一个参数
and it'll run that function with one argument
就是signal接收到的 signum
which will be the signal number that's received
为什么要将 signum 传给 handler函数
why does the signal number get into the function
如果有一个函数能处理一堆不同的信号
well in case you want to have one function that handles a bunch of different signals
这样它才知道在处理哪个信号
so you can figure out what signal its handling
用 sigaction 注册信号处理程序是一个更复杂的方法
there's a more complicated way to register signal handlers with sigaction
如果你感兴趣的话，可以看看手册
you can read the manpage if you're interested
它能让你对信号处理方法有更多的控制
it gives you a lot more control about how the signal will end up being handled
当然如果你只需要忽略一些信号，就不用麻烦了
unless you just say okay actually just ignore certain signals
这条（Access）很重要
why is this relevant well this is relevant because
你能发送任意信号给任意 ruid 和你相同的进程
you can send any signal to any process that has the same ruid as your process
发送方进程 ruid 为 X
so a sender process with a ruid of X
它能发送任意信号到 ruid 为 X 的接收进程
can send any signal to a recipient process with a ruid of X
即使接收进程的 euid 是 0（root）
even if that euid is 0
设置了suid的程序也一样
even for suid programs
这很酷
which is really cool
这意味着，可能某处运行着一个suid进程
this means that there could be a suid program running somewhere
而你对其有了一点控制能力
and at any point that you more or less control
你能让它突然收到意外的信号
you can cause that program to suddenly and unexpectedly to hit
它对可能到来的信号没有一点点防备
because it gets no warning that a signal is coming
能让程序的执行流突然转移到信号处理程序
you can make that program suddenly divert control flow to the signal handler
如果你回想一下竞争条件模块
and if you recall in the race condition module
展示错模块了，不好意思
wrong module sorry or
哪儿去了?
where'd it go
这个
there it is
在竞争条件课程中
in the race condition lecture
有这么一个概念
we had something like this
临界区
we had a critical section
我们不想线程在其中有竞争情况
that we wanted not to have competition between two threads in
我们假设
basically our assumption was that
从这个锁开始到解锁
from the beginning of this lock to the unlock
所有这些代码在运行时
all this code would run and
第二个线程
a second thread
这个程序是多线程的
this program is multi threaded
不会打断和破坏它
wouldn't interrupt and clobber these results
这适用于多线程
that works for threading
但当收到一个信号后
but a signal received here would still
执行流仍将从临界区转移到信号处理程序
redirect control flow from the middle of this critical section to the signal handler
所以处理信号是相当棘手的
so it can be pretty tricky handling signals
我们该如何利用这种发信号给任意进程的能力呢
so what can we do with this power to send signals to any process
如果程序写的不细心，我们可能会触发bug
we can trigger bugs if the program is not programmed carefully
考虑一下
consider
怪了，等一下，我更改过这张幻灯片
that's weird hold on I updated this slide
这应该
that should
好了
there we go
我将timeout_handler改为了signal_handler
I rename that timeout_handler to signal_handler
好吧，考虑一下这个程序
all right consider this program
这个程序非常简单
the program is super simple
它运行一个循环
it runs a loop and what it does is
循环中检查全局变量是否为0
it will check if the global number is 0
如果是，它会加1
if it is it'll increment it
然后减1
and then it'll decrement it
减完后全局变量应该一直是0
the global number will always be 0 at the end of this decrement supposedly
如果不是零，我们就把它打印出来
and if it's not zero we'll print it out
按理来说，应该一直不会输出
so we should never see anything being printed
但是在程序进入这个循环之前
but before the program runs into this loop
它注册了一个信号处理程序
it'll register a signal handler
用于处理 SIGUSR1
that signal handler for SIGUSR1
这是用户自定义信号
this is user defined signal 1
它是专门
it's specifically there to
留给开发人员
give the opportunity for a developer
实现程序专用语义的信号
to implement program specific signal semantics SIGUSR1
SIGUSR2也是这样
and SIGUSR2 is another one like that
好吧，不管怎样
all right anyways so
但实际上并没有什么不同
but realistically it's not different
这个信号也可能是 SIGSEGV
this could have might as well be SIGSEGV
这是发生段错误时接收到的信号
the signal that your program receives when it's segfaults
是的，你可以捕捉到那个信号
yes you can catch that signal
用它做一些事情
and do clever things with it
例如调试崩溃的shellcode
such as debug your shellcode when it crashes
好吧
all right
SIGSEGV，我的意思是
SIGSEGV uh what I mean um
当程序接收到 SIGUSR1 时
so anyways when the program receives SIGUSR1
不管执行到哪里了
no matter where it's executing
执行流将突然转移到信号处理程序
control flow will suddenly and rudely be redirected to the signal handler
num将被设为0
and num will be set to 0
一个显而易见的问题是
so the obvious question is
如果正好在这个减1处接收到信号，会怎样
what happens if the signal is received right at this decrement pointer
好吧，让我们看看
all right let's take a look
我写了这个signal.c
so I created this in signal.c
在这里
here we are
看起来没问题
looks like it makes sense right
和我们讨论过的一样
same thing that we discussed
编译
let's compile
好的
all right
运行它
we run it
当然，它不会打印任何东西
and of course it doesn't print anything
NUM为0
NUM is 0
如何攻击它
how do we attack this
我们向它发送 SIGUSR1 来攻击
we attack this obviously by sending a signal SIGUSR1 to this program
要发送很多
and we send it a lot
最终我们会遇到这种情况
and eventually we will hit the scenario
num加1后
where this runs to increment num
在num减1前
and before this guy runs to decrement it
num 被设为0
num is reset to 0
这处减1，使 num 从0变成了-1
this decrements num and turns it from 0 to negative 1
好吧，我们运行这个试试
all right let's give that a try if we run this
在另一个窗口
and then in another window
我们获取这个程序的进程id
we get the process id of this program
我们只需要发出一个信号
and we just send a signal boom
什么也没发生
nothing happened
为什么?因为没竞争赢
why? because we didn't win the race
也许是执行到其它指令时接收到的信号
maybe it got received on a different instruction
而不是在这个加1减1之间
than the one that actually then between the increment and the decrement
这里只有大概3个汇编指令，运行的非常快
there's probably three assembly instructions that run very fast
我们当然可以继续手动尝试
we can of course keep trying manually
这样成功的概率不大
that's not gonna likely yield success
当然，我们也可以像在其他竞争中那样
or we can of course as we did in other races
用循环
just loop this
先sleep 5秒
so I'm gonna put a sleep five
方便切换窗口后看效果
so I can switch over to the other window
数到五
and then we'll count to five
随着运行
and as this thing runs
我们会看到 num 变乱了
we will start seeing the number get messed up
好的，开始吧
alright here we go
3 4 5
我们的进攻开始执行
and our attack is running
如你所见
as you can see
我们持续将 num 重置为0，然后减1
we keep resetting the number to 0 then it gets decremented
有时会看到 -2
and sometimes you see negative 2
因为在接收到下一个信号之前，这个循环恰好运行了两次
because that loop happens to run twice before the next signal is received
我们关了它
actually if we kill this
然后在这里加上sleep 1
and if we put a sleep 1
如此这般，然后
we do this and then
还是设置为sleep 0.1秒吧
actually let's do a sleep of 0.1
十分之一秒发送一次信号
we sleep a tenth of a second between every signal
这样可以给它时间来减num
it'll give it time to decrement that counter some more
我们来看看效果
so let's see here we go
现在开始被我们的信号攻击
now it's gonna be hitting us with our signal
我们开始吧
there we go see
在十分之一秒内
so in a tenth of a second
我们减了5万次
we managed to decrement 50,000 times
为什么会这样呢
now why does this happen
当然
of course
执行到这两条代码之间收到信号
the signal hits between this line and this line or you know that set of instructions
Num被重置为0
num gets reset to 0
然后再减1
this gets decremented now
Num是 -1
num is negative 1
在下一个循环中，它不会被运行
in the next loop around this will not get run
因为num不等于0
because num is not 0
但它会运行
this will get run
Num就是 -2  了
num is negative 2
以此类推，它一直在减小
and so on and so on it keeps shrinking
直到下一个信号到来，把它重置为零
until the next signal hits and resets it back to zero
这就是针对信号处理程序的利用
so that was an abuse of signal handlers
这个程序中没有多线程
there's no threading in this program
但仍有竞赛
but there's still a race
这很酷
which is pretty cool
在现实世界的代码中
and in real world code
这种事经常发生
this stuff happens a lot
由不正确的信号处理程序引起的漏洞
vulnerabilities rising from incorrect signal handlers
过去比现在普遍的多
they used to be much more common than they are today
但并没有绝迹
but they're still definitely not unheard of
好吧
all right
还有一件事
one other thing to mention
有一个和这些信号相关问题有密切联系的概念：重入
these problems with signals are strongly connected to a concept called reentrancy
可重入函数是指
right a reentrant function is basically
即使被自身的实例中断也能正常运行的函数
a function that will operate properly even when it is interrupted with an instance of itself
看一下这个 swap 函数
so consider the swap function
swap函数接受两个参数
the swap function takes two arguments
两个指针
two pointers
它会交换这些指针的值
and it'll swap the values of those pointers
它使用 tmp 全局变量来实现这一功能
and it does that using a tmp global variable
tmp 保存 变量1
that it will use for one of those values
然后用 变量2 覆盖 变量1
then it'll write value 2 over value 1
最后用 tmp 覆盖 变量2
then it'll write tmp over value 2
标准交换流程
standard swap
还有一个 call_swap 函数
we have a call_swap function
它使用swap交换1和2
that actually does swap between 1 and 2
执行完它后，x是2，y是1
right so at the end of this X should be 2 y should be 1
但是这个函数是由main调用的
but that function is called by main
但它也被注册为一个信号处理程序
but it's also registered as a signal handler
如果执行到05行前，接收到 SIGUSR1，会怎样
now what happens here if right before line 5 we receive a SIGUSR1
call_swap的新实例会执行
what will happen is the new instance of call_swap will run
因为它是信号处理程序
because that's the signal handler
会调用一个swap的新实例
it'll call a new instance of swap
旧swap还在，只是中断了
swap is already running it just got interrupted
swap的新实例将运行并覆盖 tmp
the new instance of swap will run and overwrite tmp
在这个演示程序中没什么大不了的
right and in this toy program that's not a big deal
但总的来说
but in general
重入是个大问题
reentrancy is a big problem or
重入引起bug是现实存在的
reentrancy bugs are a very real thing and
记住
keep in mind
如果程序调用了不可重入函数
if your program calls a non-reentrant function
如果函数调用了不可重入函数
if your function calls a non-reentrant function
那么调用方函数也是不可重入的
then the caller function is also non-reentrant
因为如果在被调执行的时候，再次调用调用者
because then if you call the caller while the callee is executing
它将会重入执行中的被调
it'll reenter the callee
事实上，就是这种情况
in fact that's exactly what happens in this scenario
重入是一个有趣的概念
reentrancy as a concept is interesting
但不是一个很明显的概念
and not a very obvious concept
我建议你看一下维基百科上的文章
I'd recommend giving the wikipedi article a shot
以及相关的参考文献
and related references that it will link you to
这引出了如何安全使用信号的问题
so this brings us to this question of safe signal practices
我还拼错了practice，尴尬
and I missspell practice that's embarrassing
稍等一下，我改一下
one sec let me fix that
好了，安全信号实践
all right safe signal practices
信号中最重要的是
the biggest thing in signals
不要在信号处理程序中调用不可重入的函数
don't call non-reentrant functions in your signal handlers
为什么? 因为你的处理程序可能会打断
why? well because your handler might have interrupted
执行中的不可重入函数
previous iterations of those non-reentrant functions mid execution
或者又收到了另一个（不同）信号
or another signal that's received
中断了你的信号处理程序
might interrupt your signal handler's
调用的不可重入函数的执行
non-reentrant invocation of those functions mid execution
或者取决于设置
or depending on the settings
sigaction函数更改处理函数的设置
we talked about the more complex sigaction function to modify actions taken
导致信号
as a result of a signal
使用它，可以让信号处理程序
using this you can set a signal handler
能被触发它的相同信号打断
to be able to be interrupted by the same signal that triggered it in the first place
默认情况下，一次只能处理一个相同的信号
by default you can only handle one instance of a given signal at a time
如果你还在处理段错误时，又收到了一个段错误
so if you handle segfault while you receive a segfault
那么第二个段错误将
that second segfault
我不清楚段错误
I don't know about segfault
不确定段错误是否会被处理
I'm not sure how that would work
但如果在处理 SIGUSR1 时，又收到一个 SIGUSR1
but if you receive a SIGUSR1 while you're handling a SIGUSR1
默认情况下，第二个将被忽略
by default the second one will be ignored
但是如果你用 sigaction 注册并设置好
but if you register things carefully with sigaction
那么第二个信号不会被忽视
the second one will not be ignored
会启动第二个信号处理函数实例
a second instance of your signal handle will be launched
如果它是不可重入的，马上就要糟了
and if it's not reentrant you are in before bad time
要注意一点
One note
实际上malloc和free是不可重入的
actually unexpectedly malloc and free are not reentrant
如果你仔细想想，这是有道理的
this makes sense if you think about it
Malloc和free都涉及全局变量或全局结构
malloc and free both touch a global value or a global structure
就是分配缓存
that is the allocation cache
对它的修改是不可重入的
that modification is not reentrant
如果ptmalloc在修改缓存
if ptmalloc is messing with that cache
然后它在这时候被中断了
and then it gets interrupted while it's messing with that cache
这是可能发生的
that stuff can happen
如果对libc中有哪些可重入函数感兴趣
if you're interested on what library functions in libc are reentrant
有一整个man页
there's a whole manual page
如果在shell中执行 man signal-safety
if you man signal-safety
你可以查看所有信号安全实践相关内容
you can read all about safe signal practices
公共函数的含义
and implications of using common functions
以及哪些函数可以安全使用
and what functions are safe to use
好吧
alright
希望我们已经学到了很多关于信号的知识
hopefully we've Learned a lot about signals and
希望你能
I'm looking forward to see you
在练习题中探索这个概念
explore this concept through the practice problems
祝你好运
good luck